software engineering radio episode 78
fault tolerance with Bob hammer part 2
[Music]
hello everybody this is the second part
of the fault tolerance discussion with
Bob hammer the first part obviously was
last episode ten days ago if you haven't
heard the previous episode on fault
tolerance you should really go back and
listen to that first in the previous
episode we discussed a number of terms
we're using here like reliability
availability fault error failure we
talked a little bit about the fault
tolerance mindset about how to build
systems keep it simple quality versus
fault tolerance and stuff we talked a
little bit about the shared context in
which all of those patterns reside and
then we had a little overview over all
the patterns and over how this episode
is structured and stuff and we started
with discussing architectural patterns
in this episode we're going to continue
with a detection patterns and then also
look at error recovery patterns around
mitigation patterns fault treatment
patterns and then a discussion at the
end about designing with the patterns
and why Bob wrote the book so again if
you didn't listen to the previous
episode go back do it otherwise this one
probably won't make sense okay so here
we go
have fun let's look at the the second
bunch of patterns which the error
detection patterns are actually
generally the detection patterns it can
be false or arrows I guess so let's
start with fault correlation fault
correlation is a pattern that relates to
you've got these error reports that are
going into the fault observer and you'd
like to know what it is that went wrong
so you want to know what the fault is
and so forth correlation is the thing
that's looking to see have I seen this
kind of error before you know this error
signature you know do I know that this
this means that we had a bad message
that we received or do I know that this
means that we have corrupt memory
somehow and so we're taking fault
correlation as taking the detection
report you know some part of the system
detected a problem and fault correlation
is classifying it deciding which bucket
it belongs and because each of the
buckets probably has a different set of
techniques to be used to help resolve
the problem okay and the next one our
containment barrier sounds a bit like
the firewall we've been talking before
yes it is it's the firewall and it
points right back to units of mitigation
that point here is that you want to
confine the error you detect it and the
first thing that you need to do in a
fault-tolerant system is to isolate the
error you need and isolate in the
firewall sense I'm cut it off from the
rest of the system so it can't propagate
and error containment barrier is telling
you to just you to do just that okay how
do Aero spread generally it means for
example you have some bad data that is
then used or that it's passed to another
subsystem to another unit of mitigation
and that would mean that this this other
unit would also fail because it now
works with with a faulty data and that's
basically what you want to prevent right
yes exactly okay isolation is a really
really important thing and its really
really system specific and unit of
mitigation specific so it's really hard
to come up with generic patterns on how
to do the isolation because it is so
context specific mmm-hmm but one way of
doing that and that's as it happens the
next pattern is probably to check very
carefully and not just syntactically but
also to some sense in some some
semantically the parameters that that
that are for example passed in an
Operations call in another unit of
mitigation right right complete
parameter checking is the pattern and it
would argue that you should check you
know every return code and make sure
that it's correct that you should check
the value you know in addition to
checking the return code you should also
check that the return values are correct
or within the correct range that kind of
thing this is really similar to
programming by contract yeah I was about
to ask that yeah so as is contracts or
this kind of DBC stuff Allah is that
used in these kinds of systems or is it
basically well just manual
if statements in all in all those places
that are used to check these things it
from the systems I've seen it's been
manually it's been manually done with if
statements rather than any kind of
larger framework and part of the reason
goes back to predating the design by
contract yeah and then part of it goes
back to keeping it simple yeah you know
that's extra if you've got a framework
to help you do that kind of thing that's
a extra infrastructure that could have
failures and nobody's using eiffel which
would provide language support but I
guess that's out of the question anyway
right
okay the next bunch of patterns are more
or less related to to monitoring the
system system monitor or versus watchdog
versus heartbeat they all sound
relatively similar to me yes and they're
they all they work together very very
closely system monitor is kind of the
higher-level pattern it's saying to
create some part of the system that will
watch the important things so there are
some things in your system that really
have to always happen and the system
monitors saying okay set up some other
something that is going to monitor that
and then how does it do it gets to
watchdog and heartbeat and I'll go about
heartbeat first heartbeat you know the
typical heartbeat message sending a you
know a ping sending a message from one
place to another and waiting for the
response and if the response doesn't
come quickly enough assuming that the
other ones in trouble or it comes garble
assume the other ones in trouble mm-hmm
and that can go either way it could be
you know are you okay oh yeah I'm okay
or it could be a periodic you know I'm
okay I'm okay you know so it works both
ways yeah in order to do a heartbeat you
really have to put something into the
system ah because it needs to know that
it needs to send the heartbeat or
acknowledge the heartbeat yeah and there
are some cases where you just can't do
that and that gets to the watchdog
pattern and watchdog is a really good
pattern Michel Pont has some excellent
versions of it yeah and it's a really
rich area so there are lots of watchdog
patterns and typically you think of it
as being like a watchdog processor a
little timer that's doing
watchdogging but you could also put in
the software structures to have a
third-party monitor that messages were
flowing between the first and second
party and use that information to
determine whether they were operating
correctly and by doing that you haven't
modified the first two yeah you know so
you're watching it from afar watchdog
relies on existing message flow and
information whereas the heartbeat relies
on specific messages that are built in
the system specifically for that exactly
okay there's a pattern realistic
thresholds that discusses how you would
pick the appropriate threshold values to
use with the heartbeats and so on right
because if you have too much of that it
probably deteriorates the the system
performance yes it gets the system
performance or you might trigger think
that there's a fault too often or not
often enough so there's some things to
think about and so that's included in
here yeah so that leads us to the to the
metrics I guess to detect resource
acquisition problems based on existing
metrics and experience I guess yes we
talked about performance in the
introduction and perform there
probably our system performance
requirements on how the system should
perform under different workloads and if
the system is getting too many workloads
and in the telephone network case we
talk about events like a hurricane or an
earthquake and everybody wants to call
their friends or you know that new
soccer match you know everybody wants to
dial in for those tickets and that's the
worst time to be adding extra workload
to the system to tell you that you're in
an overload know you want to use
existing metrics you want to use things
that are really easy to compute really
simple and that already exists because
when you need this information about
overloads and performance problems the
most is when you have the least amount
of resources to spend computing things
hmm good point the next two patterns are
checksumming and voting I know that what
the first one is I don't know what the
second one is so why don't you elaborate
the differences okay it's interesting
workers because I haven't I've never
really thought of these two as being
that closely related so
it's interesting and every time I look
at this I learned something new
so the checksum is the traditional
checksum yeah you know compute some
value that will tell you that the value
that you computed from is correct you
know voting is used in cases where you
might have multiple redundant elements
operating and you need to decide which
of these values you're going to believe
so you get two redundant processors
computing a result which one's correct
and so you voting as a method provides
some techniques to use to help you
determine which is the correct result
when given multiple results okay that
the next two or three patterns I guess
are again related to humans or let's say
external observers they are routine
maintenance exercises and audits and and
these are related to humans as you said
but they also can be automated and the
whole point of these is you know no
system is no system should be designed
to be you know busy 100% of the time so
there's always some idle time and so
during that I don't think you know do
some routine maintenance check you know
and they could be cleaning stuff up like
garbage collection or it could be
running the correcting audits to make
sure that the data is correct routine
exercises is a specific case where
you've got an active and a standby and
you want to make sure that the standby
will work when you need it to and these
can all be triggered by humans or they
could also you know be triggered
automatically mm-hmm okay the next two I
guess are are probably also related
riding over transients and leaky bucket
counter in both cases I think that the
the problem is that you don't want to be
disturbed by well spurious errors I
guess things that go away automatically
or from without doing anything right
right and then what's the difference
between the two well writing over
transient is the bigger pattern and it's
telling you just what you said that you
don't want to waste time dealing with
problems that will clear up
automatically and leaky bucket counter
is a really classic technique for
actually implementing a counter to
determine if a problem that's an error
that you're detecting is happening often
enough that it should be treated rather
than so seldom that you can ignore it
mm-hmm and the way you do this is
literally but decrementing that the
counter with a specific speed basically
and then if the the increase because of
the error is getting bigger then you run
over a threshold and then you raise the
alarm right yes and the perfect existing
is a bucket with a hole at the bottom
right exactly that's yeah it's always
nice if patterns have real-world
analogies that you can visually picture
okay so that concludes the section on
detection patterns now that we know what
what the fault is or what the failure is
what the problem of the error is we can
now try to recover some of these things
so one of the ways for doing that is of
course if we try to contain the fault to
a specific unit of mitigation that
already well it sounds like a quarantine
right yeah so that's the first pattern
here and the first of the error recovery
patterns these are the patterns again
that are gonna take you to a new state
in the system so move the program
counter but the first thing the first
pattern here is quarantine again putting
those boundaries up to isolate because
you want to isolate the error so that it
doesn't propagate okay and the
quarantine pattern is pretty much a room
for just a reminder that you want to do
that isolation quickly before it creates
much harm the next one is concentrated
recovery what does that mean putting all
your system resources to try to solve
the problem well yes it can be it could
be putting all your system resources to
try to solve the problem or it could be
just that all the resources you put
towards solving the problem you dedicate
them exclusively to solving the problem
because if you continue trying to
receive and process new requests for
service for example everything is going
to take longer those are
for service are gonna take longer
because there's the recovery going on in
the background and the recovery is going
to take longer and so concentrated
recovery is advocating you know forget
about the new request for service while
you're doing the recovery just go ahead
and you know do the recovery as fast as
you can mm-hmm okay it sounds a bit
counterintuitive to some extent I mean
because during that time your system is
not available
yes but and and it gets to the different
kinds of reliability and availability
requirements the system might have
mm-hmm sometimes some systems are
measured based upon total system
availability and other times they're
only given requirements about partial
system availability so you have to trade
that off and again you know these
patterns have to be customized yeah for
your precise situation because sometimes
as long as you can let a little bit of
traffic or workload
you know dribble through the system flow
through the system slowly then you're
okay and you haven't you aren't
unavailable but in other cases you know
it's that's not the way things are
counted but again it it may not be the
whole system in a multiprocessor or
multiple cores you know maybe you
dedicate one core to doing the recovery
and the other we continue yeah but on
that one that's doing the recovery you
don't do any other work mm-hmm
the next one is error handler which is
probably a bit more than a simple
try-catch block I guess right the the
point of error handler it's
concentrating some of the error handling
code into one place which on the one
hand increases the complexity slightly
because now you have to transfer
somewhere and you have to take enough
context within so that you can know what
you're fixing it but on the other hand
you've concentrated that code and so you
can get you can get the faults out of it
and also it's only one place to change
when you discover you have a new
strategy or you need to try something
different the only one place to change
and you don't forget about other places
and so
there's a balancing act here and the
pattern tries to point out some of the
things to consider about having a
separate air handler versus putting it
in line okay so that's a relatively low
level implementation pattern I guess one
of the lower level ones yes but well so
people don't get Mis can get confused
none of these patterns really go to the
level of coding these are all design and
architecture level so there's still a
lot of specific design stuff you have to
do based upon them know so the next one
is restyled so that basically just means
if something goes wrong shut down the
system and restart it again yes
sometimes that's what you need to do we
try to avoid that because it takes a
long time to do the restart but
sometimes you know that's the best way
and that typically only occurs at the
end of a sequence of escalation we've
tried a number of things and none of
them have worked and so okay you know
now we'll bring out the big gun and
we'll do a restart yep
there are several less well smaller or
earlier or less escalated approaches
roll back roll forward and return to
reference point what's the relationship
between these three and what do they do
roll back is kind of the typical thing
that we're going to we encounter an
error and now we're gonna roll back and
retry yeah and you know maybe we have to
restore from checkpoint which we'll come
to in a couple of minutes but we've gone
to a previous state we're gonna retry
roll forward is for those cases where
you don't need to or it's inappropriate
to roll back and retry and so actually
roll forward is oh we're in the middle
of this transaction we've gotten an
error we'll just discard the rest of and
we'll go on to the next one mm-hmm that
kind of thing
return to reference point is very
closely related to these two but it is
more intended for the non main
application like code so you're doing a
correcting audit for example and you
know which isn't you know arguably the
main application function of processing
telephone calls or web requests
or anything and you've got an error in
there where do you go from there and so
return to reference point is putting
this is getting the signal system
synchronized again because you know you
may not need to roll back if an audit
has an error you might want to just
restart normal execution with I don't
mean the restart pattern you might want
to resume the normal execution you know
and forget about the error happening
mm-hmm so roll back and roll forward are
basically for the main application
return the reference point is for the
maintenance code if you will and restart
is like the toll system if you've got a
big problem and a rollback is basically
retry whereas roll forward is ignore yes
okay so if you if you retry there is
probably always the trade-off SN in the
in the in the heartbeat area that you
have to trade off the number of limits
you you retry the number of times you
retry the well yeah the retries if you
try too often then your system might get
stuck with retrying old crap that never
is gonna work exactly and that's it was
an important concept that I included the
pattern limit retry sin in here to
remind you to put some threshold some
limit on how many times you're gonna
retry yeah and this is exactly where
someone in charge that pattern from the
architecture huh chapter comes to play
because it's that someone in charge that
is going to be the one to say okay we've
had enough retries now it's time to
escalate mm-hm
yeah right that that was a good point
what do you do if you've reached that
them and you escalate to some other
strategy which might then be for example
roll forward or restart yes okay the
next one is failover I thought that was
a relatively general term how does that
fit into these more or less specific
strategies here well it's a we had
redundancy in the architecture chat
error and so failover is a really
important concept with regard to
redundancy and so I thought I needed to
include it and it's exactly what you
thought it was failing over we've got
one that doesn't have stopped working
and we fail
over to the other one of a redundant
pair or redundant set and resume
execution there yeah and it's not
strictly a hardware concept mm-hmm so so
there's some ideas in this pattern about
doing it with software yeah yeah okay
and the last one for this section or
chapter is checkpoint which is probably
important if you want to be able to
return to reference point or rollback
something right you already mentioned it
before by the way yes we've mentioned it
before I mean this is a really important
concept and this is one this is one of
those things that I'm sure people will
pick up the book and immediately say oh
yes okay he's got a lot of that
checkpointing it's there been whole
books written on checkpointing also it's
a very important concept and the
patterns it's again a little set
kind of like the some of the others
we've seen so checkpointing is
explaining a little bit about how it's
storing state information away can help
you recover faster mm-hmm but then
there's some empty open questions at the
end of it like what is it that you're
supposed to say what's the best
information to save in the checkpoints
and then where do you store the check
and so you know that could be a lot of
different things and then then there's
another pattern to when do you do the
checkpoint you know do you always do it
yeah well how often should you do it who
decides when it's time to do it and so
these are all covered in other patterns
within this error recovery chapter yeah
okay as a usual trade-off again if you
take point too often then the overhead
of creating the checkpoint this is too
big and if you do it too seldomly
you have to go too big well that the the
stuff you have lost is going to be too
much so well yes a lot of trade-offs to
be made there are and so I hope these
patterns will be useful to the reader to
remind them about all these things they
have to consider and trade-off sure but
but one thing that that you need in
order to be able to make these
trade-offs this is a good set of
specific requirements and would guess
that many of the people who do not work
in this like safety-critical or fault
tolerance required areas like you do
they haven't seen many of these specific
requirements specifically if we talk
about
functional requirements just always wha
yeah the system must be available it
must be fast you can't make these
trade-offs if you don't know I don't
know any more specifics that you're
absolutely right it's important to get
those requirements or without a
specification or requirement you can't
have a failure yeah you're right that
goes back to that point which is also
practical if you can't fail also a good
situation to be in
yep okay let's look at the error
mitigation pattern
patterns and they are different from the
error acock to recovery patterns again
in what sense well the error recovery
patterns are the ones that move you to
another side right so we've rolled back
to a different state you know basically
you know in a really low level we've
changed the program counter at some
weight now but there are many situations
and especially performance related
problems overloads where we don't change
the state we can do something here
locally excuse me that will allow us to
continue execution but we've mitigated
the error so these are in the chapter on
error mitigation so we've done something
to to make the world better but we
haven't changed the state okay so the
first pattern in the section is overload
overload toolboxes what's that about so
overload toolboxes I mentioned this a
long time ago also in the instruction
that knot or in relation to fault
correlation that there are different
kinds of techniques that you'll use to
resolve different kinds of problems and
overload toolboxes is pointing out that
you might have different tools to deal
with overloads in terms of memory you're
running out of memory for the
application whatever that however that
might happen you're running out of
tangible resources maybe network ports
or you know peripheral equipment or your
cpu time is going high but it's going to
be different techniques for each to help
resolve overloads of each of those
different areas and so you need multiple
toolboxes to deal with those different
kinds of problems okay you know it's
it's a classic case of you know the old
joke that
when the only tool you have is a hammer
everything looks like a nail okay and
this is trying to remind you that no
there are you know there isn't one
single solution that's gonna work with
all these different overloads okay so
then let's look at the couple of these
solutions the first one that I see here
is deferrable work so basically whenever
you can do something later do it later
my principle in life
oh yeah that's basically right we talked
about the routine maintenance kinds of
tasks those are easily deferrable you
know if the system is in overload it
must be working pretty well mmm good
already yeah if it doesn't have other
errors so the first some of that work
that would check if it's working out
well although the error the overload
might be a consequence of some fault
somewhere else because for example
something isn't DQ'd after it has been
processed so the same thing is processed
over and over and over again
yes luck and that and that gets to
another pattern reassess overload
decision which is reminding you to have
the system periodically check that it's
applying the correct techniques because
there might be more information to tell
you exactly what you said that it's a
fault and you're not dequeuing something
rather than an overload huh since we
talked about queues the next thing to do
to mitigate overload situations is queue
for resources what does that mean
sometimes you can get away with queueing
requests as they come in to process them
a little later because it might be you
know very momentary spike or it'll also
smooth the arrival rate to the point
where the processor will able to handle
it more efficiently mm-hm
but you have to be sure to do it
equitably so that everybody receives
good service in some way and again the
requirements should specify what good
service is next one is chat load right
sometimes you just get too much work in
and you need to get rid of it and so you
need to design the system and know in
advance how you're going to do that how
you're going to discard those requests
that come in that you can't poss this
process right now mm-hmm
you know ignoring deadlines just
discarding things off the queue not
putting things under the queue in the
first place or some examples of the way
you might shed load
and when you're shedding load you want
to do that very efficiently because
you're doing it in a period of overload
so you want to really be efficient in
the way you do it and not have errors
occur during that discarding yeah and so
you know final handling is another
pattern that talks about that kind of
stuff mm-hmm okay and and if you can't
shed the load you might share it with
some other component of the system as an
alternative right again the patterns are
can be applied at design time so you can
think about that where can you what
other processes are in the complex that
you're building or other cores that are
doing different kinds of work that you
can start allocating resources from when
you get to a period of overload you know
and it could be local like I mentioned
processor cores or it could be across
the network that all of a sudden you
start sending requests to different
places and these are examples of ways of
expanding the possible ways of resolving
the problem of expanding the resources
so it's an expansive automatic control
mm-hmm
and then another way is of course
instead of shedding or sharing just
doing everything a little bit slower I
guess right just slow it down just
because by doing that you keep the
system saying you are limiting what
you're doing you're shedding some work
and you're processing what you can but
you're conscious about processing
accepting only as much work as the
system can process at any given moment
and therefore you're going to keep it
out of an overload situation that could
lead to a failure or keep it out of an
overload situation that is unrecoverable
the next two patterns are fresh work
before stale and finish work in progress
how do they relate so both of these
patterns fresh work before stale and
finish work and progress are related to
the cueing fresh work before stale in
some situations especially where there
are humans on the other end like of the
telephone or of a web request you know
they get impatient if the thing doesn't
happen fast enough they're going to
resubmit it and so it's possible in some
situations to get multiple requests that
are identical in the queue
because the person has resubmitted them
and so you want to take fresh work
before stale so you get the most recent
request and then by the time you get to
the old requests you'll have some
indication that it should definitely be
ignored finish work-in-progress deals
with transactions that must complete and
and maybe the things that are long-lived
and so you know there might be a lot of
messages that get received or the system
has significant work time invested in
seeing that they complete and so you
want to do what you can to make sure
that they're allowed to complete and
maybe defer some new work requests to
allow the continuation of these others
already in the system this fresh work to
fall stylist is something that's
probably used in many telephone systems
I guess because I've had that experience
if I try to call some whatever call
center and I don't get through I just
hang up and try again and and now I
can't get through so it seems like
that's something that's used quite a bit
yes it's a very common thing and some of
these patterns in this chapter
particularly like fresh work with for
sale and finish work in progress were
first written in pattern form by Gerard
Meszaros who worked for another telecom
company and so this is building upon
lots of good Telecom experience and some
of these overload handling techniques
marked data as the next pattern yeah go
ahead no I'm sure you say what you're
just gonna say that it sounds a bit like
checksum that you somehow hi mark data
with some property so you can check
whether it's correct but I'm not sure if
that's appropriate no it's the next one
after this error correction code is like
that it's error correction code is
taking in is giving some redundant
information so that you can reconstruct
the correct value if if for example the
checksum says it's incorrect now the
mark date is a little different it's
sort of like the I Triple E not a number
standard or Ward Cunningham had a
pattern that was related to and it's
you've got a data value it's incorrect
you know it's incorrect you can't figure
out what it should be made equal to you
can't use so the correcting audit can't
correct it
instead of that you put a flag on it
they lets everyone know this value isn't
correct don't use it but then you let
that data value and its flag ripple
through the system and the system just
respond oh that I can't use that value
mm-hmm um that might mean if you want to
use this mechanism in a system that
instead of just using an integer or
somewhere you might use a struct that
holds the int as well as some kind of
markup some kind of confidence value or
whatever which in turn might be a
performance hit so is it is it fair to
say that in reliable systems and
fault-tolerant systems you might be
willing or you will have to take that
performance hit that performance
overhead or memory overhead to get the
benefit in in reliability yes that's
going to be true that there are going to
be extra overheads in memory and
processor time associated with being
fault tolerant and those are mitigated a
little bit by the fact that we want to
keep it simple yeah but you're very true
that it's either you're gonna have to
trade some resources off so the the cost
aspect you talked about before or fault
tolerance is not free wasn't just about
the the money or the effort you put into
designing the system it's also that you
have to tolerate certain runtime
overhead to be able to detect and and
monitor the system and defaults and the
arrows that's correct
kind of obvious not that I think about
it ok that concludes the arrow
mitigation pattern section and that
leads us to the last pattern section
which is about fault
treatment so this is about looking at
the root cause and solving the real
problem right yes in real time the
system has detected the error or fault
hopefully before it became a failure and
we've done the recovery or mitigation
steps the system's back operating
normally and now it's time to really fix
the fault
you know correct that misplaced comma
yeah and so these are some patterns that
do that to help you do that ok but they
don't happen automatically at runtime
there is something that that's more or
less again process stuff what do you
manually do how do you release the next
version of the software or something
like that yes okay so that's
first look at the world let's look at
the first of the pattern is called let
sleeping dogs lie sounds nice
yes and I don't know if this is an
expression that translates well and if
if it's a common thing that you've heard
before it's a bit different in German
it's called a Beca con - laughs and in
Haeundae which means don't wake Sleeping
Dogs up but it's kind of say okay
and I've heard that before so and and
the point is that there might be some
faults in the system that aren't worth
fixing it's better to leave this fault
there even though they might cause an
error again than to fix it because maybe
the fix would have to be really really
complicated and so if it's really
complicated you risk screwing it up and
introducing more faults or maybe it's in
functionality that is really set used
seldom so it's not worth the effort to
actually make the correction because
it's going to be such a low probability
event so let's leapings life's die
is meant to point out to the reader that
just because there's a fault you should
think about whether you want to fix it
but of course that's only true if you
have a system that is fault tolerant ie
doesn't completely fail as a consequence
of that fault
exactly okay that's an important thing
it doesn't it's not about recommending
not to fix bugs you should only not fix
those bugs if they aren't going to
result in a serious problem right you'd
need to do the the cost-benefit analysis
of you know the cost of fixing it and
risk of fixing it and the benefit of
fixing it out and weigh all that
together
yep next one is reintegration and
reintegration is discussing when you are
actually making the fix when you're
putting it in that you should have some
predefined process or method to actually
put it in you shouldn't just go in and
start typing and assuming it will work
the same every time so write down how
you're going to do it develop a
procedure and this is partly because a
concept that we didn't talk about
earlier is that experience has shown
that failures in system
are related to either the hardware the
software or the it's we call it a
procedural error so something human did
and so you want to have a procedure a
process or someone to follow so we can
reduce the number of those procedural
errors okay the next one is reproducible
error what's that about
reproducible error is basic testing to
to make sure that you can really
reproduce the error you know so that
you've really identified what it is and
then fix it and if you can't reproduce
it in the laboratory okay why not you
know is maybe you don't know precisely
what it is and so make sure that you can
reproduce it and so it's basic testing
to be able to find that you you be sure
that you really have the same error that
occurs so you know what the fault was
and then after you fix it after you
think you fix it that you really gotten
it out of the system as it basically
means first try to really nail the
problem down before you in a hurry try
to fix something yes okay yes that was a
very good short summary okay
small patches is probably than the idea
of just changing a little bit of the
system instead of redelivery the whole
big thing right and this will be
governed by the tools and the languages
you know a whole bunch of other
constraints upon your contacts but you
know smaller patches result in fewer
hiding places for other faults and you
know fixing faults within patches is a
well-known problem that is is best
avoided the fix on fix problem yeah yeah
that's the whole point if you just
insert a small piece of patch it then
you don't necessarily know how it might
affect the rest of the system so you
might you might change something that's
actually incompatible with the rest of
the system creating new box or false
yeah yeah yeah but again it's dependent
on your tool yeah but in any case even
if you just deliver a small patch you
probably have to retest right that's
right and that gets to the reintegration
pattern so the rear aggression would
discuss
the test after you think you've
installed your small patch to make sure
that it was installed correctly
interview yeah okay the route cost
analysis is the next pattern again you
said this really early once we have an
error we want to fix the root cause we
don't want to fix just the symptoms and
the root cause you know could be in many
levels deep and this is another place
where the fault tolerant mindset comes
in and one simple technique which is
what I write about in the book is to ask
a series of wise - you know why the why
did this happen
yeah and then you've come up with the
answer well why did that happen and just
keep answering a series of wise kind of
until you get tired of it or until you
reach what you think is a written really
the root cause of the problem or the
best thing to just level to fix it like
a stack trace and and the last pattern
of the sections to revise procedure it's
probably then basically fixing a Fault
in in the procedures if it's a Fault in
the you in the operation of the system I
guess write procedural errors account
for a significant number of problems
that are reported like in the u.s.
telephone network and just because
you've produced a procedure for help
with reintegration
you should feel willing to make changes
to it if it doesn't work you know so
it's possible that that root cause
analysis is going to point to some human
error that was done somewhere you know
and it could be during the design and
coding level and so feel free to change
those procedures and those methods also
to make them more robust yeah ok this
concludes our discussion of the patterns
that was really alone a long thing here
but I mean now that we know the patterns
we don't necessarily know what to do
with them that's more or less always the
problem with patterns they give you a
toolbox of well more or less little or
big strategies of doing things but but
there is still a big gap to making you
an expert to fault-tolerant systems and
so one one issue is how do you work with
these patterns how do you design an
architect systems with these patterns so
do you have any recommendations there
what people actually do
now except for obviously buying and
reading the book so they get multi tails
and this is something I've been saying
for a long time and about the way to use
patterns is I think the best way to use
patterns you know in these
fault-tolerant patterns are really any
is to become familiar with the patterns
that are out there and then when you're
confronted with just with a design
problem you can say oh yeah I think I
saw a pattern about that and then you
can go and find it and refresh your
memory on what the things are yeah and
so become familiar with with these
patterns and the other patterns and then
when you're confronted with a new design
problem think about okay state where
have I seen patterns about dealing with
state and fault-tolerance with regard to
state and you know so start thinking
about the patterns in terms of your
domain problem domain and you might
think oh the system I'm building doesn't
have any state that really gets saved so
I don't even need to pay attention with
the checkpointing patterns yeah yeah and
so you've got this big pool of patterns
like from this book and all the other
books and then when you come with a
design problem pull out those patterns
that are most applicable and then start
using them when you do your architecture
and your design yeah one way I like to
look at it in the way that I talk about
that with people is that assume you're
designing your system and you have this
multi-dimensional design space it's a
big empty space initially and this
initial empty space is populated with
some matter basically and these are the
patterns they they're basically like a
specific well-defined points in that
n-dimensional space so you wander around
you build your system you talk about
something you've read a pattern you get
near this pattern ah you're you you
basically gravitate to that pattern
you're now on that pattern you think of
how you can use that pattern is it
sensible to and need to tweak the
pattern a little bit and if so use it
and then just go on designing your
system and you might find more of these
gravity sources of patterns as you as
you go along mm-hmm yes that sounds
really good I haven't heard that
expressed that way before but that
sounds good
it's
well came up in discussions with with
people about patterns
well yeah it's nice nicely visual so to
conclude our discussion why did you
write this book well obviously because
you want systems to be more reliable I
guess but wasn't there any material out
there before no that was the big
disappointment that there are a number
of really good books about soccer
reliability engineering or there are a
few books about software reliability
techniques but they don't really convey
the range of solutions there's some
books that might focus on inversion
program or that kind of flavor of stuff
and then a whole lot of books that talk
about doing the analysis and might have
a little bit about some of the
techniques and so I I was always looking
on my bookshelf and never seeing the
book that I wanted about that had a you
know they're really the tips to help
designers build fault-tolerant systems
mhm
not how to analyze them but how to build
them and so that's the niche that I'm
hoping to fill with yeah I mean I've
read several of your patterns before
since I'm obviously also quite involved
in the patterns community and I've
always looked forward to seeing them in
a book so I really I really like this
stuff that's also why I although I'm
building these kinds of systems but as
you said everybody should have some of
these things in their mind because it
just makes the toolbox if of software
architects and designers and developers
a bit bigger with regard to certain very
important points or some important
aspects of software development so I
think it's a really good really
interesting and good book and I'm
looking forward to read the printed
version good thank you then thank you
very much for being on the show
you're very welcome thank you for
inviting me no problem thanks
[Music]
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want to get
more information about software
engineering radio or if you want to give
us feedback please go to our website at
se - radio dot net you can also contact
the team at team at SAE - radio net
although we prefer entries in our
comment system on the website so other
people can see what you think software
engineering radio wants to thank Henning
Cowley for the intro and outro music as
well as Lipson for providing the
bandwidth this episode of se radio as
well as all other episodes is licensed
under Creative Commons license
see the software engineering radio
website for details